<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preached before His Majesties High Commissioner; and the Estates of Parliament By the appointment of the provinicial Synod of Lothian and Tweddale. Upon Sabbath the 7th. of May, 1693. Unto which is subjoyned the sermon preached at the opening up of the Synod. May 2. 1693. By Mr. William Vetch minister of Peebles.</title>
            <author>Vetch, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896039</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896039</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95845)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2375:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preached before His Majesties High Commissioner; and the Estates of Parliament By the appointment of the provinicial Synod of Lothian and Tweddale. Upon Sabbath the 7th. of May, 1693. Unto which is subjoyned the sermon preached at the opening up of the Synod. May 2. 1693. By Mr. William Vetch minister of Peebles.</title>
                  <author>Vetch, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by John Reid, to be sold by Alexander Henderson, book seller in the Lochen-booths,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D ² D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Moſt Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi>. William Marquiſs of Lothian</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:3"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS PREACHED Before His MAJESTIES HIGH COMMISSIONER, And the ESTATES of PARLIAMENT. By the appointment of the Provincial Synod of <hi>Lothian</hi> and <hi>Tweddale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon Sabbath the 7th. of <hi>May,</hi> 1693. Unto which is ſubjoyned the Sermon Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the opening up of the Synod. <hi>May</hi> 2. 1693.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>William Vetch</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Peebles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Haggai,</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Col:</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>Edinburgh, <hi>Printed by</hi> John Reid, <hi>to be ſold by</hi> Alexander Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon, <hi>Book ſeller in the Lochen-booths,</hi> Anno 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:4"/>
            <head>UNTO HIS GRACE WILLIAM DUKE of HAMILTON THEIR <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> HIGH COMMISSIONER For the Ancient KINGDOM of SCOTLAND, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MAY it pleaſe your Grace, If I had an Offering, that might be any way Acceptable, There is none to whom it is ſo much due, as unto your Grace; And that becauſe I drew my firſt Breath, and had my firſt Education, where the Ancient, and Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Dowglas</hi> was the Grand Planet, Regnant in that <hi>Hemiſphaere.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:5"/>
            <p> Secondlie, Your Grace, by the Alwiſe Providence of <hi>GOD,</hi> and the Choice of our Great, and Gracious Proteſtant King, being made his Majeſties High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner to this Parliament: Stand in the place of <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> in my Text, and are chiefly concerned to notice, What <hi>GOD</hi> calls for at your Hands, in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Building up the <hi>walls of Our ſecond Temple,</hi> the foundations whereof have been wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie and mercifullie laid ſome Years ago; And now, Your Grace, and this Honourable and High Court of Parliament, are again called to carrie on this begun Work, both by the Providence of GOD, that hath put a New Opportunitie in Your hands; And the Call of the Preached Word Awakening and ſtirring You up unto the Work. And O that Your Grace, and this Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Court, may give ſuch a ſpeedie Return to both theſe Calls as this <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Government did: For we may ſee from the firſt chapter of this propheſie of <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai,</hi> that within the ſpace of three weeks &amp; three daies; after this Prophets firſt ſermon, they fell zealouſlie to the work, and that with great courage and unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie; And alſo without anie further delay, or anie viſible diſſent among them, and whereas the ſtouteſt of them before had no great mind to the work, now when alarmed by the Prophet, in the Name of the LORD, the verie weakeſt and moſt timorous, are forward, and bold to carrie it on. Thirdlie, And who could be ſo fit in all the Nation for this Work, as Your Grace; Being not onlie of ſo <hi>Noble a Deſcent,</hi> where <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153710:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>Courage</hi> has been remarkablie for ſo manie Ages <hi>Connatural to the Family:</hi> (And let it not be loſt in You, eſpeciallie when called to lay it out on ſo <hi>Noble an Interprize,</hi> as the <hi>Propagation</hi> and <hi>Protection</hi> of <hi>Religion, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property:</hi>) But alſo, being advanced to Repreſent the <hi>Chief Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> of the Kingdom, and whom GOD has bleſsed with a Goodlie Perſon, Excellent parts, a Numerous, Noble, and Hopeful Progenie: A Bleſſing that fitts You to ſpeak with Your Enemies in the gate; And that <hi>Divine Hand,</hi> that has now promoted Your Grace, to ſo high a Truſt, wherein Ye may do great things for the Advancement of CHRISTS Kingdom, will look for ſome proportionable Return: If the Great <hi>Land-LORD</hi> of the World expect a Rent from the meaneſt Cottage: What a large Revenue muſt he look for, from ſo great Families; For, <hi>to whom much is given, of them much will be required.</hi> Learn to pay this, and it will draw down not onlie Bleſſings on Your ſelf, but on your Poſterity. It was the Honour of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Houſe, that from Father to Son, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> many Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they were Heirs of the ſame Promiſe. <hi>Heb: 11.9.</hi> O that there were ſuch a Succeſſion to be found in the Houſe of the Nobilitie, and Gentrie of our Land: But alace Plentie abuſed, diſpoſes to Sin, and Vice: And it is toe Ordinarie for the Greateſt, and braveſt Spirits, to think the Power of Religion, a baſe and mean thing, which taketh off from their Grandeure,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:6"/>and Eſteem among men, and that the ſtrictneſs of it, is inglorious: But a Conjunction of Goodneſs and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs together, is the moſt Lovelie and comfortable thing in the World; And greatneſs without Goodneſs will be a Taſtleſs Cordial at the Long Run.</p>
            <p>I have preſumed to thruſt theſe following Sheets un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Your Graees <hi>Patrocinie,</hi> being perſwaded that a Favourable Smile from ſuch a <hi>Potent</hi> Prince, will give them ſufficient Protection; And although the Fab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick be mean, yet the <hi>Statlineſs</hi> of the <hi>Frontiſpiece</hi> may beget a Curioſity in many to look into it: hoping that your Grace will Pardon wherein <hi>I</hi> have preſumed, and will Favourably accept of the ſmal token of my Sincere affection to your Grace, and thoſe Noble Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies (for they that have not Gold muſt offer <hi>Goats</hi> Hair) I make Bold to ſubſcribe myſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your GRACES Moſt Humble Servant, In the LORD, <hi>WILLIAM VETCH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:6"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER</head>
            <p>THERE is none in my Station, (I confeſs) ſo unfit to appear in Print, as I am, But the reſtleſs importunity of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons of all ranks, occaſions me to do violence to my own inclinations, in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing the enſuing ſermons; which you have here laid before you, with little addition, or alteration: Only let me tell you, that although I opened up this text, <hi>Haggai</hi> 2: 4. As it referred to the preceeding and ſubſequent verſes of the Chapter, by way of Lecture, and did intermit according to the Cuſtome; yet I have thought fit to put it, and the Forenoons Sermon together as one Entire Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Another Reaſon moving me to this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking is, That ſeveral things ſpoken in that Great Auditory upon this Subject, are Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:7"/>Miſtaken, and Miſ-improven, which this may be a mean to Cure, and Remove.</p>
            <p>The Entertainment I acknowledge is ſo Courſe and Mean, that I cannot promiſe it an univerſal Acceptance: Seeing too too many in our Day, (wherein Fancie and Opinion, that Witch and Enchantreſs has got the Aſcendant of Religion and Reaſon) are more devoted to what may pleaſe their palat, then prolong their health, and life. But if it may (as it is) be any wiſe ſerviceable to the publick good of the Church, and the work in hand, and any way profitable to any particular well wiſher, of that Intereſt; I have attained my End. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>One of ZIONS Well-wiſhers, And thy Servant, W. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:7"/>
            <head>The Firſt SERMON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>HAGGAI <hi>2: 4:</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Yet now be ſtrong. O <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> ſaith the LORD, be ſtrong, O <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſon of <hi>Joſedech</hi> the high Prieſt, and be ſtrong all ye People of the Land, ſaith the LORD, and work: For I am with you, ſaith the LORD of Hoſts.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Shall for Lecture open up theſe words, as they referr unto the preceeding and ſubſequent part of the Chapter, and obſerve ſomethings from them, and then go on, and proſecute that Doctrine, which I think moſt ſuitable to this Occaſion; I ſhall not have time to give a large, or Critical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of the Text, with Reſpect to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons mentioned in it, or the Prophet that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered this Meſſage, or annent the time that he was ſent to that People, for fear I come ſhort of the main things I purpoſe to ſpeak to this Honourable <hi>Auditorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do not read that this People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to whom this Propher <hi>Haggai</hi> was ſent, had immediately after their return from the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Captivity, any Prophet among them, and
<pb facs="tcp:153710:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet they had ſuch as were able to direct them in their work: But they proving ſinfully and ſhamefully negligent and ſloathful, for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable while after their return, in the work of Reformation which GOD had called them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: And for which they had the Civil Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity even <hi>Cyrus</hi> his grant. The LORD at length raiſed up this prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> and after him <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariah,</hi> to awaken and ſtirr them up to their dutie, in carrying on this Work that was begun ſeveral years ago.</p>
            <p>Their neglect and careleſneſs in this matter was occaſioned partly from their own timerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and weakneſs, being but few when compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with their Anceſtours who builded the firſt Temple, and with the multitude of Enemies that at preſent oppoſed them, &amp; no wonder they were timerous, having been ſo long houled and kept at under in <hi>Babylon.</hi> Where their long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and Captivitie had diſpirited them.</p>
            <p>Partly this neglect was occaſioned from the bold and violent oppoſition of enemies that did what they could to mart the begun work of GOD in the Land; Such as <hi>Sanballat</hi> the <hi>Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,</hi> and his Complices.</p>
            <p>Partly from their too too much minding the things of the world, and preferring them to the things of GOD, as we have them reproved for it
<pb facs="tcp:153710:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>chapter 1ſt. ver. 4th. Is it time for you, O Ye, to dwell in your Cicled houſes, and this houſely waſte? and this is a diſeaſe that abounds much in our days!</p>
            <p>This ſecond chapter wherein my text lves, is full of encouragement for them, to proceed in the work, notwithſtanding of the diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on the one hand, and the oppoſitions they met with on the other.</p>
            <p>The firſt encouragement lys in the latter words of the text, from the promiſe of GOD's Preſence with them in this work, <hi>For I am with You, ſaith the LORD of hoſts: therefore be ſtrong and work;</hi> you need not fear all your enemies that oppoſe you, when I am with you.</p>
            <p>The ſecond encouragement for removing their timerouſneſs, and ſpiriting them to their work is taken from the ſtanding Covenant that was between GOD &amp; them, &amp; that of a long &amp; old date, even ſince the day that he had brought them out of the land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> where we have to admire GOD's faithfulneſs to them in keeping this Covenant, when they were guilty of many breaches thereof to him. Verſe 5. <hi>According to the Word that I covenanted with you; when ye came out of</hi> Aegypt, <hi>ſo my Spirit remaineth with you, fear ye not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Encouragement to go on in their
<pb facs="tcp:153710:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>work is taken from the Lords promiſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe the external deſpicableneſs and meanneſs of this fabrick they had begun, and about which they were ſo diſcouraged, becauſe it had not that Extenſiveneſs and Largeneſs of Building, neither had they <hi>Solomons</hi> riches to give it that internal ſplendor and Glory that <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple had, all this the LORD promiſes to make up, with his own Glory and the Mediators perſonal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, verſe 7: 8, 9.</p>
            <p>The 4. <hi>encouragement</hi> to proceed in the <hi>begun work</hi> is: that although for their neglect they were fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen under many Judgements, and eſpecially that of famine, as in the preceeding Chapter <hi>Verſe,</hi> 6. <hi>Ye have ſown much, and brung in little,</hi> and alſo in this Chapter, <hi>When they came to an heap of twenty Meaſures, they proved but ten, when they came to the Preſs to draw out fifty Veſſels full, it filled but twenty, Verſe</hi> 16. By which ye might eaſily have conjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured that I had a controverſy with you; And itconcerned you to have enquired unto the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of my controverſie: But now ſayes the LORD <hi>If ye will proceed in the work, O</hi> Zerubbabel, Joſhua <hi>and the people. I will remove theſe Judgements, and bring Bleſſings in the room of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt Argument which is very conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to move and encourage them to go on in their work, and ſhould have great weight with
<pb facs="tcp:153710:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>us; Who are affraid of the Nations about us is the LORDS promiſing Safety and Security to them, in the midſt of great Commotions, and deſolating Judgements upon the Nations round about; As if he would ſay, though I make Kings and Nations fall by the Ears and deſtroy one another, though you may hear it or ſee it, yet it ſhall not come near you, and this ye ſee in the laſt verſes of the Chapter, and it is like that ſweet Promiſe to the Church, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 91.7, 8. <hi>Verſes, A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand: But it ſhall not come nigh thee; Only with thine eyes ſhall thou behold and ſee the reward of the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Verſe</hi> we have read to you more, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly we have theſe things to be conſidered. 1. The Exhortation <hi>be ſtrong</hi> and work, this is the Call which the LORD ſends by the Prophet <hi>Haggai.</hi> 2. We have the perſons to whom this Call and Meſſage is directed and ſent, and that is to <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and to all the People: Magiſtrates Miniſters and People, they are the Perſons to whom this Call comes. 3. We have the perſon calling, and that is the LORD of Hoſts, by his Prophet <hi>Haggai.</hi> Thus ſaith the LORD of Hoſts. 4. We have the Arguments which the LORD makes uſe of in this <hi>Verſe,</hi> to preſs them unto the giving of a Cordial and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:153710:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Obedience unto this Call and Meſſage, and theſe Arguments are two, which ye would do well to take notice of, one of them is taken from the Patience of GOD, another is taken from the Promiſe of GOD. That which is taken from the Patience and Forbearance of GOD, lyes in the firſt Words of the <hi>Verſe</hi> (yet now) after ſo long a foreſlowing and neglect of the Work in you; (as if the LORD would ſay) and after ſo long Patience and Forbearance in me, it concerns you to fall upon this Work that I call you to, I might have come and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed you after I brought you out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> for your unanſwerableneſs to My Command, yet have I forborne and ſtretched out My Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience towards you, and put a new opportunity in your hands, and given you a new Call, ought not My former Patience and Forebear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and My preſent Goodneſs to lead you to Repentance, to mourn over and redreſs the wrongs that you have been formerly guilty of.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument that he backs this Call withall, is in the laſt words of the Text, and that is the promiſe of his being with them in this undertaking, <hi>For I am with you ſaith the LORD of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5ly. We have this meſſage delivered with a double note of attention, to the leading men in Church and State, (perſons too incident to be
<pb facs="tcp:153710:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>heedleſs) importing no leſs than this, that it concerned ſuch as them at this verie Juncture, to give ready Obedience to GOD's Call, to be Zealous, and ſo a good example, to all the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ople under them: this note of attention calls all to take ſpecial notice of GOD's Meſſenger now unexpectedly ſent to them, and alſo of the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that he carries.</p>
            <p>And then in the laſt place we have this remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keable, Thus ſaith the LORD, thrice repeated, the deſign of which I take to be this to clear, &amp; confirm them in this call, as if the Prophet <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai</hi> had ſaid, <hi>it is not my meſſage,</hi> a <hi>ſick-brain fancie,</hi> or notion of mine, but it is the command of JEHOVAH the <hi>Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might obſerve from theſe words ſeveral things; As</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That the People of GOD may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a <hi>wonderful caſt of Providenee,</hi> and an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>Hand of GOD,</hi> out of great trouble and affliction, to carrie on a work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and yet when they are moſt clearly called to it, it may meet with great Rubbs and and impediments: You ſee they were called to this, and yet it meets with great oppoſition; and they alſo notwithſtanding of GODS Call, were careleſs and ſuperficial in proſecuting this ſo great, ſo neceſſarie, and ſo profitable a work.</p>
            <p n="2">(2lie.) I might obſerve this, That the LORD
<pb facs="tcp:153710:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>takes ſpecial notice of His people, how they manage precious opportunities for His glory, his Churches good, and the advancement of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which are put in their hands, and therefore he ſends this Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> to reprove their by paſt diſobedience and negligence, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken them to their dutie for the future. But the main Doctrine which I take to comprehend the very ſcope of the words is this, <hi>That it is the dutie of all ranks of people in a land, to be ſtrong and join cordiallie and unanimouſlie together to carrie on a begun work of Reformation, when the LORD eminently calls them to it, &amp; promiſes to be with them in it.</hi> And this is the Doctrine, that through the LORDS Aſſiſtance, I purpoſe to ſtand on, in proſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof, I ſhall follow this method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſhew you what is meant here by, <hi>(be ſtrong)</hi> and that I ſhall do firſt poſitively, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what it truely imports. 2. Negativelie, what it prohibites.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I ſhall give you the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the doctrine, why all ranks of perſons in a Land, ſhould be ſtrong and join cordially together, to carrie on a begun work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, when the LORD eminently calls them to it.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, <hi>I</hi> ſhall give you the uſe of all; This is the work that lyes before me. Firſt,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>then by <hi>Being ſtrong,</hi> is poſitively, and plainly meant in Scripture phraſe, to take courage and reſolution, that perſons of all ranks, whom GOD calls to his Service, ſhould put on cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and reſolution, eſpecially ſuch as GOD ſets up in publick Offices; Ye may ſee this clear in the caſe of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> in his firſt chapter, verſe 9, When the <hi>LORD</hi> calls furth <hi>Joſhua</hi> to inſtall him in a publick Office, which he was to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage for bringing the People of <hi>GOD</hi> through <hi>Jordan,</hi> out of the wilderneſs, and to bring them to the poſſeſſion of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and to go before them as their Captain General in the Warrs, by which they were to execute <hi>GODS</hi> threatned judgements in deſtroying theſe Nations that were accurſed, and were to meet with manie a bloodie Rancounter in the doing thereof; how does the <hi>LORD</hi> in order to all this, encourage <hi>Joſhua,</hi> in this 9 verſe, <hi>Have not I commanded thee? Be ſtrong, and of a good courage, be not afraid, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be thou diſmaid, for the LORD thy GOD is with thee, whitherſoever thou goeſt.</hi> Magiſtrates are to be men of courage, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Thou ſhalt</hi> (ſaith the <hi>LORD</hi> to Moſes,) <hi>provide thee able men, out of all the people, ſuch as fear GOD, men of truth, hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing covetouſneſs.</hi> The Original word in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, <hi>is men of courage and ſtrength;</hi> Yea, they that are in publick Office muſt not only put on
<pb facs="tcp:153710:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>courage and reſolution, but they muſt evidence it in the right management of the truſt put in their hands <hi>Nehemiah</hi> chap. 6.11. <hi>Should ſuch a man as I flee;</hi> Nay, I will neither fear, nor flee, but ſtand it out againſt <hi>Sanballat,</hi> and all his Complices, and all their power, their ſcoffs, their threats, their plots, this was the Anſwer he gave to ſuch as were telling him ſuch fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtories. That the Enemies would be too ſtrong for him, that they would runn him and that work down, that he was come from <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes</hi> with a new Commiſſion to propagate and carrie on; but he puts on Courage and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution as an Antidote againſt all theſe Fears: I ſay, That perſons that are Magiſtrates and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and ſuch as have a publick Truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them by the <hi>LORD,</hi> ſhould be men of great courage, eſpeciallie in a time when Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and Temple-work is in hand, as in my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> was a man of courage, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.25. to the 30 verſe, when he told King <hi>Saul</hi> plainlie his ſins, And <hi>That GOD had rejected him therefore, and rent the Kingdom from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elijah</hi> alſo was a man of great Reſolution and Courage, as you may ſee in that conference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Obadiab</hi> and him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. ver. 15. &amp;c. And when he told a threatning <hi>Abab,</hi> ver. 18.
<pb facs="tcp:153710:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>That it was he and his fathers houſe that troubled Iſrael, in that he had forſaken the LORD and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Baalim.</p>
            <p>And the Prieſts of the <hi>LORD</hi> were men of Courage; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.17, 18: when they reſiſted King <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> invading the Churches priviledges</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. I take this to be meant by <hi>(be ſtrong and work)</hi> to be Livelie, Active, and diligent, in the work which they were now called to by the LORD, that they not only have a fittedneſs for their work, but that they be faithfull and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in the diſpatch of it, and indeed I find that the Wiſe man. <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 9: 10. does com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend diligence &amp; activitie in all a mans lawful buſſineſs in the world: <hi>Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might, &amp;c.</hi> How much more commendable muſt it be, to be active and diligent in the great concernments of GOD and of His Houſe, and Glorie, that muſt be a thing much more regarded than the concerns of our own houſes; And that 1ſt becauſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God are preferable to our matters, that is the thing, that ſhould be upon the heart, and Conſcience, and affections of everie perſon, of publick truſt, they ſhould ſet the matters of GOD foremoſt, like thoſe perſons, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 137 <hi>ver:</hi> 5, 6. <hi>If I forgetthee, O Zion; If I preferr not thee, to my chief Joy, let my right hand forget her cunning;
<pb facs="tcp:153710:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153710:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153710:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> This diligence and Activitie for <hi>GOD</hi> and his matters with which we are entruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is the diligence that brings in the greateſt Reward: though alace it is little believed; there are many of you that hears me this day, that if you would lay out your ſelves in places and ſtations for <hi>GOD</hi> and his work, it would bring you a greater reward, than you are aware of, and you will be made to ſee that your neglect in this thing will be of dreadfull conſequence at the long run, and that the perſuite of the things of the world, which divert you from this main buſineſs, will bring you no comfort, and be of no ſignification, except it be to diſquiet your conſcience, and increaſe your torment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From this conſideration, People of all Ranks ſhould be moved to great Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Activity and Dilligence in the Matters of GOD, becauſe the Enemies that oppoſe this Work, are very diligent, lively and active, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 38.19. <hi>Verſe, But mine Enemies are lively, and they are ſtrong, and they that bate me wrongfully are multiplyed.</hi> The Godly man complains here of his Enemies (you ſee) That they were ſtrong and livey, but does this diſcourage him; Nay, but on the contrare, it awakens him to a more vigorous proſecution of his Work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This Exhortation being directed to
<pb facs="tcp:153710:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>all ſorts of Perſons, States-men, Church-men, and Commons (to <hi>be ſtrong</hi> and work) it calls all thoſe cordially to unite and joyn together to build up the Temple of GOD, whoſe founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are already laid, and then they ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the Propheſie of the latter dayes, <hi>Zeph:</hi> 3.9. <hi>For then will I turn to the people a pure Language, that they may all call upon the Name of the LORD to ſerve him with one conſent:</hi> And as the words are rendred in the Originall Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, they ſhall ſerve the LORD with one Shoulder; I ſuppoſe that many may have heard of the Father that had a great many Sons, and when he was going to make his Latter Will, he called for them, and commended unto them a keeping of Unity, and Harmony to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in their Converſe and Buſineſs, which would greatly tend to their Comfort and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and to demonſtrate this to them, he cauſed bring a Sheaf of Arrows, cloſely tyed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and gave them to the Eldeſt to break, but he could not breake them, and ſo he gave them to the Younger ſuceſſively, and they could not break them, but when they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, they were eaſily broken, ſo it is with Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and People in the Land; When they unanimouſly and cordially joyn together in the Work of GOD, they cannot
<pb facs="tcp:153710:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>eaſily be broken, and deſtroyed; We ſay, <hi>vis unita fortior,</hi> and Unanimity in the work of GOD when all joyn together as it were with one Shoulder without lying by, or interfeir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or drawing back, or obſtructing one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other is a good taken of a thriving work, when Magiſtrates make ſuch Laws as authorize only the true worſhip of <hi>GOD,</hi> and take care to ſee them duely execute, that ſuch as hinder uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in Religious Worſhip may be remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſo the Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, Government of the Houſe of the <hi>GOD</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, may be according to the Laws of the <hi>GOD</hi> of heaven through the whole Land: For purity of Doctrine does not conſiſt in a Lawleſs Liberty or Tolleration for men to do, and ſay what they pleaſe in matters of Religion: But it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in a joynt uniformity to Worſhip <hi>GOD,</hi> according to his own precept, and this promiſe (they ſhall all ſerve the <hi>LORD</hi> with one Conſent) which was calculate for the latter days: So much then you ſee is implyed in this Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>(be ſtrong) viz:</hi> Courage and Reſolution, Activity and Diligence, with Unity and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <p>In the next place I come to ſhew you nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively what this Exhortation <hi>(be ſtrong)</hi> prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, or what is not meant by it. As 1. It for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids
<pb facs="tcp:153710:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>timorouſneſs, for men to be poſſeſſed with a humane or ſlaviſh fear, that keeps them back from their Duty to <hi>GOD,</hi> and His Work in their Station, this is a thing very unbecoming to ſuch as are <hi>Zerubbabels, Joſhuas,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiahs,</hi> ſhould ſuch perſons as they fear, Whom had they to be affraid of, but curſed <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and ſuch as were no better in after Generations: What could <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and theſe that were with with him be affraid of, when he was come from <hi>Babylon,</hi> cloathed with the Kings Letters and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, in order to the carrying on of the forſlowed work of Reformation; ſurely he had not the King, neither the <hi>GOD</hi> of Heaven; nor the honeſt party of the Land to be affraid of; I know none that might be a terrour to him, and them that were joyned with him but the <hi>Gerizzim</hi> party, who were ſinfully united to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe violently and cunningly the building of the Temple, and the true Worſhip of <hi>GOD,</hi> that they would ſo gladly have deſtroyed: Let me ſay it to this Honourable and High Court of Parliament without offence, and in all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, what have you to be affraid of, that you ſhould be Faint hearted in the Work of GOD; ſurely it cannot be of the GOD of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nor of our Gracious King and Queen, not of the Proteſtant Princes abroad, nor of ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:153710:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>as are true Proteſtants at home; ſure all theſe will be Cordial Friends to our carrying on the Work of Reformation, and when ye have all theſe on your ſide, you may well <hi>be ſtrong,</hi> and put on Courage and Reſolution, for you have a mighty great backing: But of whom are you indeed affraid? Is it of the Pope, or of the <hi>French</hi> King, and his Allies, or is it of the <hi>Geriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zim</hi> party of theſe Lands, That they get up their head again, and that ye and your Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Eſtates be ruined? Surely the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives of <hi>Aegypt</hi> will riſe up in Judgement againſt you, who were in worſe Circumſtances then you are, and yet were not affraid of the wrath of the King, but even over the Belly of Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Laws befriended the Children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> How much more ſhould ye whom GOD in his Providence has raiſed up to Midwive out the Churches deliverance, and are under the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of no bad Laws, to frighten you from your work: Put on Courage and Reſolution to help your Travelling Mother the Church, to bring forth the Man-Child of a Glorious Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and then I may promiſe ye ſhall be bleſſed as theſe Midwives were, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.21. Of whom it is ſaid, <hi>becauſe they feared the LORD, be made them houſes:</hi> That is he preſerved, and Increaſed, Propagated, and Enriched them and
<pb facs="tcp:153710:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Familys. Will you read &amp; believe that Scripture, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 51.12, 13. verſes, compared with the 7 verſe, <hi>I even I am be, that comforteth you, who art thou that thou ſhouldeſt be afraid of a man that ſhall die, and of the ſon of man that ſhall be made as graſs, and forgetteſt the LORD thy Maker, Who hath ſtretched forth the Heavens, and laid the foundations of the Earth? And haſt feared continualie everie day, becauſe of the furie of the oppreſſour, as if he were readie to deſtroy, and where is the furie of the oppreſſour.</hi> And verſe 7. <hi>Fear ye not the reproach of men, neither be afraid of their revilings.</hi> For verſe 8. <hi>The Moth ſhall eat them like a Garment, and the Worms ſhall eat them like Wool, but my Righteouſneſs ſhall be for ever, and my Salvation from Generation to Generation.</hi> But if theſe Enemies were never ſo formidable, and numerous. Let me beſpeak you as the Leaders of the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> did their Armie, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4: 9. <hi>O Be ſtrong and quite your ſelves like men;</hi> do your duty with Reſolution, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and Faithfulneſs, and the LORD ſhal be with you to deliver the Land from theſe Task-Maſters: But if <hi>ye be not ſtrong,</hi> &amp;c: then you may provoke GOD to let us fall before the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins,</hi> even at <hi>Ebenezar,</hi> verſe 1. and 2. The place where GOD has hitherto helped, will you take that prophetical Encouragement for the latter dayes to animate you to the work,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.32. <hi>For tho ſuch as do wickedly againſt the Covenant, be Corrupted by Flatteries, yet the People that know their GOD ſhall be ſtrong and do Exploits:</hi> And if there be ſtill any of you falſe and faint-hearted, in the Matters of GOD and the King, then I Proclaim <hi>Gideons</hi> Proclamation, <hi>Judges.</hi> 7.3. <hi>Whoſever is fearful and afraid, let him return and depart early from mount Gilead:</hi> And that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, <hi>Deut:</hi> 20. and 8 verſe, <hi>And who is there that is fearful and faint-hearted, let him go and return unto his houſe, leſt his Brethrens Heart faint as well as his Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, This Call, <hi>be ſtrong and work,</hi> thrice repeated, and thrice backed with, <hi>Thus ſaith the LORD,</hi> prohibites all further delay of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, this People had done it too too long. You that are Magiſtrats, Miniſters, and people would delay this buſineſs no longer, for by ſo doing: 1ſt. You diſcourage friends, and begets many fears in them, and doubtings what may be the Iſſue of ſuch delays, and whether this begun work will thrive or not, and this cannot but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a great deal of ſorrow in the hearts of the Godly,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> This gives great encouragement to the oppoſite partie, and puts a further opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in their hands, to gather to a greater ſtrength againſt the preſent work, to marr it, and if they
<pb facs="tcp:153710:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>could to overturn it: yea your fears and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs gives the enemies to take greater heart and Courage: Therefore let me ſay to you as the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> did to <hi>Joſhua, chap.</hi> 10, 6. <hi>Slack not thy hand, from thy ſervants, come up to us quickly and ſave us, for all the Kings of the</hi> Amorites, <hi>that dwell in the mountains are gathered together againſt us.</hi> You ſee the ſad effects of a ſhort delay, <hi>Exod:</hi> 32, 1. When <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtayed but fourty days u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the mount, the people fell to Idolatrie, and what if your lingring to bring us out of the ſad, I had almoſt ſaid, <hi>Sodom like ſtate,</hi> that we have too long been into; draw down remarkeable Judgements on us, as it did on that people. <hi>Gen:</hi> 19, 16, 17 <hi>ver:</hi> and are there not many of the people of <hi>GOD</hi> crying out, as it is <hi>Judges</hi> 5, 28. <hi>Why are his Chariot wheels ſo long of coming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This Call in my Text (<hi>be ſtrong,</hi> &amp;c.) prohibits a Laiſh careleſneſs, and a <hi>Gallios</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concernedneſs in the great matters amongſt your hands, and calls for Seriouſneſs, Wiſdom, and diligence in the managing of ſo great a Truſt, and not to be like that People, of whom it was ſaid, <hi>they dwelt careleſly, Judges</hi> 18.27. <hi>They were a quiet and ſecure people, and the</hi> Danites <hi>came upon them, and burnt their City with fire:</hi> Ye know <hi>Gallios</hi> Character, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.17. verſe, <hi>He cared for none of theſe things:</hi> And is there
<pb facs="tcp:153710:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>any thing <hi>under Heaven, that we ſhould be ſo much concerned about,</hi> or <hi>careful of, as the Work of GOD committed to us.</hi> And Magiſtrates, and all other perſons concerned would often Remember, that as it is <hi>Great Truſt,</hi> that is committed to them, ſo they muſt <hi>Anſwer for the right or wrong Management</hi> of it before an <hi>Impartial Judge,</hi> which ſhould make us to endeavour ſo to act in our Station, as we may be approven, and accepted of him in that day. But peradventure this Argument will have greater weight with many, GOD in His Providence, hath put our Religion, Libertys, and Properties in one bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, and he muſt have been very blind that did not ſee, that when our Religion was almoſt gone, our Liberties and Properties were follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard, and running the ſame fate, the one was going with the other. Therefore we would do well to have a ſpecial reſpect to, and care of the Work of GOD, now while we are called to recover it, and eſtabliſh it, for it is the ſureſt mean, for preſerving our Liberties and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and if we neglect the one, GOD may be provoked, to permitt our Enemies to Robbe us of all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> This Exhortation <hi>(be ſtrong)</hi> ſeeing it calls (as we have ſaid) to unitie and Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie) ſo on the other hand it prohibites Magiſtrats,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Miniſters &amp; people to fall into diviſions and fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for that will indeed make them weak, &amp; ſo mar, &amp; retard the work they are called to, If Satan &amp; his inſtruments can make <hi>GODS Miniſters</hi> and people, to differ and claſh among themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, they know it will prove a notable mean to forſlow the work of GOD among your hands; <hi>divide &amp; impera</hi> is a Stratagem ſtill made uſe of in all Ages; and it is not out of faſhion yet, and O that we may not have no more reaſon to lament the diviſions of our <hi>Reuben, Viz:</hi> (our rulers as the firſt born were) with that Lamentation, with which <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> Lamented their diviſions, becauſe they came not out to help the LORD againſt the mighty, but abode among the ſheepfolds; when they were eminently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, to ariſe and unanimouſly to appear, and joyn for the reviving of the Work of <hi>GOD,</hi> that was lying in the Aſhes, and though all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>GOD</hi> in the Land were called to joyn with them, from all Corners; and help them in this work; Yet many lurked and withdrew, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Undertaking might not proſper, and then if they had joyned, their Eſtates would have been Ruined; how was <hi>Deborah,</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab</hi> affected with this, as we may read in that doubled Lamentation, <hi>Judges,</hi> 5.15. and 16. verſes, verſe 15. <hi>For the diviſions of</hi> Reuben,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>there were great thoughts of Heart, and theſe diviſions the more they thought on them, were more deeply affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; wounding, &amp; therefore they muſt ſigh and lament it over again.</hi> verſe 16. <hi>For the diviſions of</hi> Reuben, <hi>there were great ſearchings of heart enquiring (as it were) what might be the cauſe of theſe lamentable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, as alſo what might be the Cure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the Reaſons of the Doctrine, which ſhew you why all Ranks of people in the Land, ſhould <hi>be ſtrong</hi> and joyn cordially and unanimouſly together to carry on a begun work of Reformation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. Becauſe it is <hi>GODS</hi> Work; the building of His Houſe, and the reforming of His Church from corruptions that it has been defiled with; is the moſt Honourable, Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and ſpecial Work, that <hi>GOD</hi> calls the Children of men to, in this World. <hi>David</hi> did ſee, and think it to be a very Honourable and Excellent Work, when he made ſo many, and great preparations to bring home the Ark, which was fourty years out of its place: When he muſtered up Thirty thouſand of the choſen men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to bring it from <hi>Kirjath Jearim:</hi> and we may not only ſee his fortitude and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in this Undertaking but his Zeal, as ye have it ſet down, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 132. <hi>I will not go up to my bed, nor give ſleep to mine eyes, nor ſlumber to mine
<pb facs="tcp:153710:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>eye lids, till</hi> I <hi>find out a place for the Mightie GOD of Jacob.</hi> And when they came to the Ark, you ſee what is their ſupplication. Verſe 8. <hi>Ariſe, O</hi> LORD <hi>to thy reſt; We are come to carrie GOD back again;</hi> (ſo to ſpeak) and the Ark of GOD, that has been ſo long out of the Land, and out of the Sanctuary, we ſee alſo how glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he would have been at the building of the Temple, and what preparations he had made for it, But when he ſaw that the honour was to be conferred upon his Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> how does he preſs him to forwardneſs, and faithfulneſs in that matter. 1 <hi>Chron:</hi> 22. to the 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Now my Son, The LORD be with thee, only the LORD give thee Wiſdom and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; and give thee Charge concerning Iſrael, that thou mayeſt keep the Law of the LORD thy GOD, then ſhalt thou proſper, if thou takeſt heed to fulfil the Statutes and Judgements, which the LORD charged</hi> Moſes <hi>with concerning Iſrael: Be ſtrong,</hi> &amp; of good Courage, dread not nor be diſmayed: So that you ſee what eſtimate this great and holy man, put upon the work of GOD, and how concerned he was about it, as the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal buſineſs he had to do in the World, and 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 2.30. verſe: GOD hath ſaid, he that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours me, I will honour. O how dangerous is it, to have an opportunity put in our hand, to ſerve GOD, and his Intereſt: and not to guide it well, and what ever figure any of You
<pb facs="tcp:153710:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>may make in the World; yet you only ſignify ſo far in the ſight of GOD, as You act for him in your Station and Generation, and do you not know, that many may ſtand for a great ſumm &amp; make a great figure in the eyes of men, that will ſtand but for <hi>ciphers</hi> in <hi>Heavens Arithmetick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſon ſecond. As it is GODS Work ſo he viſiblie, clearly, and eminently, calls us to it, and that by theſe ſix Calls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> By the call of his word; for the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation we are called to, is that which is ſuited unto GODS Law, contained in his written Word, and the LORD hath Honoured <hi>Scotland</hi> beyond many other Nations of the World, in that he hath written unto us the great things of his Law, <hi>Hoſea,</hi> 8.12. O that we may not count them a light thing: And may it not be ſaid of us; as <hi>Pſal:</hi> 146: 19, 20: <hi>He ſheweth his word unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>his ſtatutes and his Judgements unto</hi> Iſrael. <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with every Nation.</hi> Have we then GODS Laws, His Statutes, and his Judgements, then certainly we have them either for ſomething, or nothing, and can they be given us for any thing elſe, but to direct our ſervice and obedience to GOD, and is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you, the honourable members of this Parliament, that will make Laws and promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatt them, and would not take it ill, if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:153710:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>did not Obey: Would you not Judge ſuch diſobedient perſons to the Law to be Rebells, and puniſh them accordingly: Of how much ſorer puniſhment will they be found worthy, that take no heed to the Laws of GOD, reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in His Word, that they may give a Conſtant and Conſcientious Obedience thereunto.</p>
            <p>Now the Reformation that we are called to is moſt ſuitable unto this Divine Law, which has been owned contended for, and witneſſed to by the Godly party in the Land, and that of all Ranks both while they lived, &amp; when they dyed, and that as the pureſt Reformation of any <hi>Proteſtant Church;</hi> and this was teſtifyed many years ago, by a great man of this Nation; who Bleſſed GOD that he was born in a Church, whoſe Reformation was purer then that of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Geneva:</hi> And ſeeing we have Ordinances, Means, and Opportunities again put in our hands: Perſons of all Ranks had need to take Care to manage them ſo, as we may give a good accompt of the Truſt committed to us. But leaſt I tranſgreſs too far and treſpaſs upon your patience. I ſhall Cloſe at this time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:21"/>
            <head>The Second SERMON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>HAGGAI <hi>2: 4:</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Yet now be ſtrong, O <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> ſaith the LORD, be ſtrong, O <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſon of <hi>Joſedech</hi> the high Prieſt, and be ſtrong all ye People of the Land, ſaith the LORD, and work: For I am with you, ſaith the LORD of Hoſts.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THERE is nothing more to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the Sons of Men, then this one thing, that we have ſinned our ſelves unto ſuch a benighted and dark Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that we can neither take up our danger aright to flee from it, nor our Duty, and what is the righteſt ſeaſon for the right performance the reof: So that in this Caſe we are more to be pittied then the beaſts of the field. <hi>For the Ox knoweth his Owner, and the Aſs his Maſters Crib; But Iſrael doth not know, My Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doth not conſider:</hi> Iſaiah, 1.3. Yea, <hi>Jer:</hi> 8.7: <hi>Yea then the birds of the Aire, for the ſtork in the Heaven knoweth her appointed times, and the Turtle and the
<pb facs="tcp:153710:21"/>Cran, and the Swallow, obſerve the time of her coming, but My People know not the Judgement of the LORD;</hi> And is it not a great peice of Condeſcending Love and Mercy in GOD, that when we neither know nor conſider our Work, nor the ſeaſon of it, he Condeſends to ſend Meſſengers to put us in mind of both; This people when they proved Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent in the greateſt and moſt Important bunneſs, in which their happineſs was folded up: He ſends the Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> to tell them what they had to do, and what they had neglected, and that if they would mourn for what Sins they had committed, and what duties they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected, &amp; be zealous and careful for the future in anſwering and obeying what GOD called them unto, all bygones ſhould be bygones. (If I may ſo ſpeak) yet <hi>now be Strong,</hi> &amp;c. You know the Doctrine I was upon: That it is the dutie of all Ranks of People in a Land to joyn Cordially and unanimouſly together to carrie on a begun work of Reformation, when the LORD Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently calls unto it, and promiſes to be with them in it. I am come the length of the 2d. reaſon of the Doctrine, to ſhew (this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Auditory) that as this work, is the work of GOD, ſo he doth Eminently call you to it, and that firſt by the call of his word, as
<pb facs="tcp:153710:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>I have touched: for if the Laws of Heaven given to the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> did obliedge them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all Idolarrie, and falſe worſhip, and to reform and worſhip GOD, preciſely according to the Divine Iuſtitution, do they not equallie oblige us, are they not the rule in our day, as well as they were in their day, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not given us theſe ſtatutes, laws and Judgements for that very end, that he gave them to the Church of old, which if we do we ſhall live in them, and which if we diſobey and deſpiſe, they will not a little contribute to aggravate our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Call, To carrie on a begun work of Reformation, is that of eminent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable providences, when there has been nothing for many years, but a mixture of ſad things to the Land, and the work of GOD in it, carried on by the <hi>black Horſes,</hi> and <hi>ſpeckled Horſes,</hi> (if I may ſay ſo) ſtrange and ſad diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of Providence, whereby <hi>Jacob</hi> was given to the <hi>ſpoil,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael to the Robbers,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we were brought unto the brink of the pit, &amp; ready to periſh, all our expectations failing us u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the right and left hand, giving all up for loſt, both our Civil and Sacred concerns, that at ſuch a nick of diſtreſs as this, the LORD ſhould by his wonderful providence raiſe up a
<pb facs="tcp:153710:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Deliverer to his own Church, another <hi>Cyrus;</hi> Yea and greater then <hi>Cyrus,</hi> to give us ſuch Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from our bondage, as we are Witneſſes to this day, this is a thing that Remarkably calls us to obſerve the doing of the LORD, and he who ſees it not to be the doing of <hi>JEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH</hi> muſt be lamentably blind: And does not our great and Gracious King; be ſpeak you the Honourable Members of Parliament in the words that <hi>David</hi> beſpoke his Princes. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.17 <hi>Verſe,</hi> To the end: <hi>David alſo commanded all the Princes of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to help</hi> Solomon <hi>his Son, ſaying, is not the LORD your GOD with you; and hath He not given you Reſt on every ſide, for he hath given the inhabitants of the Land unto mine hand, and the Land is ſubdued before the LORD, and before his people.</hi> Verſe, 19 <hi>Now therefore ſet your heart and your Soul to ſeek the</hi> LORD <hi>your</hi> GOD; <hi>Ariſe therefore, and build ye the ſanctuary of the</hi> LORD GOD, <hi>to bring the Ark of the Covenant of the LORD, and the holy Veſſels of</hi> GOD <hi>into the houſe, that is to be built to the Name of the</hi> LORD. This is a thing that any thinking Perſon, when they ſeriouſly conſider: Cannot but admire, and ſay, that this is a remarkable and Eminent call of the providence of GOD, to carrie on a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun work of Reformation when ſuch an unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and unexpected opportunity is put in
<pb facs="tcp:153710:23"/>our hands, and I am ſure nothing will make his Majeſtie more renowned in after Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World, than that he has keeped ſo juſt a proportion, between his firſt declarations for the ſaftie and good of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and his future actings; and in this he Acts like the high and Noble Family of whom he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, who have been the great Protectours, and Propogators of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> and is not this a new call of his Providence: that though we theſe years bygone, have not ſo well manage opportunities pur in our hand, for advancing the work of GOD; he gives us this one opportunity more: For if he had not ſhewed his more then ordinary care theſe years bygone to preſerve the work that he had begun, and to keep the Ark in its returning from being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by ſpecial caſts of providence, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun deliverance had been utterly fruſtrated, and ſpoiled by our ill management; but O that we could admire the wiſdom and goodneſs of GOD (and I take it as a Token for good) that he has preſerved his begun work over the Bellie of the cunningeſt and ſtrongeſt devices of adverſaries, and of the undexterous and careleſs management of friends.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third Call,</hi> To carrie on the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, is from our <hi>Mother</hi> the Church of
<pb facs="tcp:153710:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that natural dutie, and becoming kindneſs, that we owe to her, as ſuch who is not yet got out of her Ruines, ſhe calls to us who are her profeſſed Children, as the Jewiſh Church did of old to hers, by the Prophet <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iah</hi> Chap: 51, 18. <hi>verſe. Is there none to guide her among all the Sons whom She hath brought forth? is there none that taketh her by the hand, of all the Sons that She hath brought up?</hi> They would be counted unnatural <hi>Children,</hi> that would no help their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Mother, that gave them a natural life, out of her afflictions and diſtreſſes; how much more unnatural Children muſt they be, that will not help that Mother out of her miſeries and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles (Eſpecially when an Eminent Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is put in their hands) from whom they pretend to derive a Spiritual and Eternal Life: They that refuſe to do this, they evidence them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be baſtards, and not true ſons of the Church. Theſe perſons hearts are like to that Mother, that ſaid to King <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſhe <hi>would have him to divide the Child,</hi> but the true Mother was of another Sentiment, who ſaid <hi>I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye ſhould be Mother,</hi> falſe as you are than the Child ſhould be divided; And by this ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered her naturall Affection. I ſay then, we Evidence, our ſelves to be Baſtards, and not true Children of the Church, that are nor for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing
<pb facs="tcp:153710:24"/>the work of the Houſe of GOD, for ſetting up all the Pillars and Ordinances there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The Doctrine, Diſcipline, Worſhip, and Government of the Houſe of the GOD of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, according to the Laws of the GOD of Heaven, (the work muſt not be divided) and doing what in us lyes <hi>Nehemiah</hi> like, for that end, he was a man concerned in the City of his GOD, and ſepulchres of his Fathers that were lying waſt, he was a man that ſought the well-fare of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> And what did he? I will tell you what he did, he obtained Letters from the King to Reverſe Letters and Orders that the Enemys of GOD had received for hindering of the building, for you will ſee in the Book of <hi>Ezra,</hi> Chap: 4: from the 4: verſe, <hi>That the people of the Land who were Gerizzim party did exceedingly weaken the hands of the people of</hi> Judah, <hi>and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them in the building.</hi> And verſe 5: <hi>They hired Counſellours againſt them to fruſtrate their purpoſe,</hi> &amp; the S. verſe gives an account who they were, <hi>Rehum the Chancellour, and Shimſhai the ſcribe, and the reſt of their Companions,</hi> mentioned verſe 9. And when they obtained theſe Letters, they ſoon put them in execution to marr the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of the People, and Work of GOD; as you ſee in the 23: verſe, of that Chapter, <hi>Now when the Copy of Artaxerxes Letter was read before
<pb facs="tcp:153710:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Reburn, and Shimſhai, the ſcribe and their Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they went up in haſte to Jeruſalem, and to the Jews, and made them to ceaſe by force and power, &amp;c.</hi> But honeſt and good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for this, and was at no quiet till he procur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Letters from the King, that his ſtop might be taken away, that ſtood in the way of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, he is made the Remarkable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to diſcover this plot, that was for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturning the new begun Work of GOD and removing the impediments, and was never at reſt till he got the Work ſet on foot again.</p>
            <p>Now if the LORD in His Wonderful and gracious Providence, raiſe up ſome ſuch Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier or Cup bearer in our day (<hi>Nehemiah</hi>-like) when the caſe of our Church, and the Work of GOD in the Land, runs ſo much parallel with this, to get the plots and Plotters diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that opoſe this begun Work of GOD, the Letters ranverſe, and the Impediments remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Inſtructions from the King, to carry on the begun Work of GOD; Should not this be obſerved, as a new and Eminent call of GOD, for Clearing, Confirming, and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging all Ranks of people in the Land, to build up the Walls of the LORDS Temple a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; And in this glaſſe of Providence may we not ſee clearly, that new Plots are like
<pb facs="tcp:153710:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>old Plots, new Oppoſition to the Work of GOD, like the old Oppoſitions, and new De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances like old Deliverances.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> Call to carry on this begun work of Reformation, is from the Noble Examples and Preſidents in Scripture, who when ever the Providence of GOD put an opportunity in their hands, opened the doors of the Houſe of the LORD, ſet up the Inſtituted Worſhip of GOD and removed the corruptions and defilements that <hi>Idolaters</hi> and others had brought unto the Temple, ye ſee a famous Inſtance of this Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of our Imitation in that good King <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 29: and 3: verſe, <hi>He in the firſt Year of his Reign, in the firſt moneth, opened the doors of the houſe of the LORD, and repaired them, and he brought in the Prieſts and the Levites and gathered them together unto the Eaſt ſtreet; and ſaid unto them, Hear me ye Levites, ſanctifie your ſelves, and ſanctifie the houſe of the LORD GOD of your fathers, and carrie forth the filthineſs out of the holie place.</hi> Verſe 6. <hi>For our fathers have treſpaſſed, and done that which was evil in the eyes of the LORD our GOD, and have foreſaken him, and have turned away their faces from the habitation of the LORD, and turned their backs, &amp;c.</hi> See alſo what good <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> and tender <hi>Joſiah</hi> did in this matter, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering and Advancing the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation;
<pb facs="tcp:153710:25"/>as they were great men, ſo they were greatly concerned in their day and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for the Truths of GOD, for which they bear an honourable and ſavourie charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in all Ages, while others that were oppoſers of GODS work have a black mark put upon them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fifth Call,</hi> To carrie on this work of Reformation, is from the eminent Apoſtaſie, and abounding wickedneſs, and profanitie that has followed thereupon in our Land; great backſlidings, as they call for great Repentings, ſo alſo for Remarkable and great Returnings; eſpecially when GOD gives unto People repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted calls thereunto: and have not we had ſuch Remarkable and Repeated Calls, both from the VVord, and eminent providences; GOD has again and again ſpoken to us in that lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage that he ſpoke to His Church in the days of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> as you may ſee in his third chapter the 1, the 14, and 22 verſes, where we have the call for Returning thrice repeated, And O that the Inhabitants of our Land might give in ſuch an anſwer as is recorded in that 22 verſe, <hi>Return ye backsliding children,</hi> there is the Call, <hi>and</hi> I <hi>will heal your backslidings,</hi> there is the motive, And O that we could give in ſuch an anſwer as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>Behold we come unto Thee, for Thou art the
<pb facs="tcp:153710:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>LORD our GOD.</hi> O ye who pretend to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the work of Reformation, will ye ſee if ye can prevent Souls from going down to the pit: Let there be ſuch Laws made and revived, and carefully put in execution, as may ſuppreſs crying and abounding abominations, inconſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a true and through Reformation, ſuch as Sabbath-breaking, ſwearing, drunkenneſs, and whoredom, the predominant ſins in our Age, that cannot but draw down vengeance on the Land if not prevented. As alſo, all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſm errour, and ungodlineſs, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeaſon of doing this is put in the hands of Magiſtrates and Miniſters, if they joyn not together and make a right uſe of it, for the end given, then it is likely to draw down that threatned judgement, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. verſe, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have purged thee, and thou waſt not purged, thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filthineſs any more, till</hi> I <hi>have cauſed my furie to reſt upon thee.</hi> And that judgement which our Saviour pronounced upon that people who had a day and ſeaſon of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and Salvation given them, but they made ill uſe of it, and therefore you ſee, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41. how He laments their folly, (and that with tears,) before He pronounce their doom, <hi>if thou hadſt known even thou, at leaſt in this thy day the things which belong unto thy peace, but now they
<pb facs="tcp:153710:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>are bid from thine eyes.</hi> And we know not how ſoon the day may come, when our Enemies ſhall caſt a trench againſt us, and lay us and out Temple even with the ground, becauſe we know not the time of our viſitation; VVe never read that Chriſt wept but twice, and one of them was at the proſpect of the death &amp; burial of His Ancient Spouſe, the <hi>Jewiſh Church:</hi> VVe have had a Three years and an half Goſpel-day, which is thought to have been the time that CHRIST the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> after He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to preach the Goſpel, ſhined in the Orb of Goſpel Ordinances unto this Church, And yet that day proved not the day of their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but only of their Tryal, and of ripening of them for a more deſolating ſtrock of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, under which they ly unto this very day, And may we not be affraid that this be our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry caſe, for we have had as long a ſeaſon, and are like as badly to improve it: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may put this Queſtion to one and all of you to reſolve; VVhether this be a time of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or a time of deliverance that we are under? (for ſeveral judicious Chriſtians do doubt of it) But you who are the Members of this Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parliament have an opportunity to put in your hands, which if you manage well, may give a deciſion unto this Queſtion: And O
<pb facs="tcp:153710:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>that you may have wiſdom, Courage, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution given you ſo to do.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſixth Gall,</hi> To carrie on this begun work of Reformation, is GOD's promiſe to be with you, whom he calls and employs in this publick ſervice, and this is plainly, and I may ſay power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully expreſt in the laſt words of the Text (<hi>for</hi> I <hi>am with you</hi>) this is a clear and Comfortable promiſe, and then he backs it with power and Authority, and O that it might be ſo upon our hearts, when he ſays, I <hi>am with you ſaith, the</hi> LORD <hi>of hoſts,</hi> This tittle JEHOVAH is thrice repeated, but in the laſt place it is thus expreſt the LORD <hi>of hoſts,</hi> which muſt import ſome what beyond the former two, and has certainly a great Emphaſis in it, the ſcope of which I take to be for removing their fears, and ſtirring up their Zeal and Courage: As if he would ſay ye are but a few ct weak Companie to undertake the Reformation, who have been in miſerie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivitie, and firy furnace of a prolonged affliction, and ſo have not that Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage that is neceſſarie to carry on my work: But if you would ſtudy and endeavour to have right uptakings of me, as the LORD <hi>of hoſts,</hi> Stronger by far than all your Enemies, then ye will not be affraid to go on in the work, when you ſee I am able to ſecure you againſt all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions;
<pb facs="tcp:153710:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>And indeed right uptakings of GOD and his promiſed preſence, will be argument e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to put <hi>Life</hi> &amp; <hi>Courage</hi> in the moſt timor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Member of this houſe, to act vigorouſly for GOD and his intreſts, when inferiour Creatures are backed with ſuperiour, they will put on cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and venter far: a cowardly Souldier or Servant when he is under a couragious Captain or Maſter, will be quite another thing than alone how much more ſhould Magiſtrats, Miniſters, and people be valiant for the truth, when they have GOD to own them. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 118, 6. <hi>The LORD is on my ſide: I will not fear what man can do unto me:</hi> and how ſafe and ſecure will that Land &amp; that Church, be about whom the <hi>LORD</hi> will be as a wall of fire; whatever carnal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may ſay to the contrair, and to have <hi>God</hi> not only to be a wall of fire round about, But to be the Glory in the midſt of us, muſt be a deſireable ſtate, for as this will reflect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort upon us who are lodged within ſuch bleſſed Boundarie, ſo it will reflect terrour upon the Adverſaries, which will make them not only not to come neat, but to flee away as you have it; <hi>Pſal:</hi> 48.3.4.5. and 6 <hi>Verſe. GOD is known in her palaces for a Refuge. For Lo, the Kings were Aſſembled they paſſed by together, they ſaw it, and</hi> ſo they marvelled, they were troubled, and
<pb facs="tcp:153710:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>haſted away, fear took hold on them and pain as a Woman in Travel: And O what a Rich promiſe have we for ſuch a ſecuritie, if we will but anſwer GODS Call, and be found in our dutie, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.5. <hi>For</hi> I <hi>ſaith the Lord, will be unto her a wall of fire round about, and will be the glorie in the mdſt of her:</hi> Why ſhould we be affraid, for if we under ſo many eminent Calls of GOD, and ſo many gracious promiſes of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and conduct, then we are under a Captain General that never failed his Church, &amp; can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh their compleat deliverance, over the greateſt enemies that oppoſe it, he can lay <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> and his Army in the deepths of the Sea, and divide the mighty waters that his Redeemed might paſs through, He can make the little hills and great mountains to get out of the Way, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 114, verſe 3. <hi>The ſea ſaw it, and fled, Jordan was driven back, The mountarns skipped like Rams, &amp; the little hills like Lambs:</hi> why what was the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, could not thou O Sea, have kept ſtill thy ordinary motion and currents? &amp; you little hils and great mountains your ordinary poſture, and place, and have ſtopped the deliverance of the Church out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and their march towards <hi>Canaan?</hi> Was it the terrour of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and his hoſt, or of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the armies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that made you quite your ground, and
<pb facs="tcp:153710:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>give way: No, no, it was for none of theſe, if they had not been headed by the Mighty <hi>GOD</hi> of <hi>Jacob;</hi> it was the preſence of <hi>JEHOVAH</hi> that made the Earth to tremble, the depths dry up, and the mountains get out of the Churches way: verſe 5. What ailed thee, O <hi>thou Sea, that thou fleddeſt? Thou Jordan, that thou waſt driven back? Verſe</hi> 6. <hi>Ye mountains that ye skipped like Rams, and ye little hills like Lambs? ver.</hi> 7. <hi>Tremble thou Earth, at the preſence of the LORD, at the preſence of the GOD of Jacob.</hi> What need you fear then to throw down the Groves? Repair GODS Altar, and build His houſe, <hi>Gideon,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> like, when the LORD of Hoſts is with you: may you not clearly ſee, that your help is in the <hi>Name of the Lord,</hi> but your fear is in the name of man! Are you <hi>Zerubbabels, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuas,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiahs?</hi> Perſons in publick Truſt? then ye ought to carry like <hi>God,</hi> becauſe ye are in <hi>Gods</hi> place, And carry by your Offices that Tittle in the World, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. <hi>I ſaid ye are Gods, &amp;c.</hi> And among other things ye ſhould reſemble Him in Courage, and Holineſs, are none of the leaſt. What a vile ſight is it to ſee a drunken <hi>god!</hi> or a ſwearing <hi>god!</hi> (if I may ſo expreſs it) And how unbecoming a thing is it alſo to ſee a trembling <hi>god!</hi> You that ought to be a terrour to others, and would be ſo, if you
<pb facs="tcp:153710:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>manage that Office and Truſt aright, with that Courage, Reſolution, and Boldneſs, yet when you faint in it, in order to the work of <hi>God,</hi> it ſayes that other perſons, and inferiours too, are a terrour to you.</p>
            <p>Now for removing of this diſtemper of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and ſlaviſh fear, that Courage and Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution may take its place. Let me recommend this one Remedie unto one and all of you, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſuch as ſtand in publick Office, and it is a cure with a <hi>(probatum eſt)</hi> tryed, and left to Magiſtrates, and Miniſters, by that great man <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 11.27. verſe, it is ſaid there, <hi>He feared not the wrath of a King, as ſeeing Him who is inviſible:</hi> And yet any might think he had great reaſon to be afraid of ſo potent an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, who with his Anceſtours had detained the Church in bondage for four hundred years, and ſo it is like queſtioned neither his power, nor his right to detain them; But the Text tells you what was the Antidote againſt this fear, <hi>Viz. That by Faith be ſaw Him who is inviſible;</hi> his faith was at work in <hi>heaven to get God</hi> to <hi>counſel, aſſiſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> him, while his hands were at work on Earth, to relieve the Church and people of <hi>GOD</hi> from their Long and ſore Bondage, I wiſh that all the great Ones of the Land, and eſpecially ſuch as are in publick Office had the Exerciſe of this Faith, by which they might
<pb facs="tcp:153710:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>take up the <hi>Almighty power of God,</hi> and his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where Preſence,</hi> that ſo their fears and faint-heartedneſs, might be removed, if <hi>Moſes</hi> had been poſſeſſed with many peoples fears <hi>in our day;</hi> it's like he would have made an Act of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and Compounded with <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and ſo matted the Churches deliverance: This was the Remedie, that good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> alſo made uſe of, to encouradge his Subjects and Souldiers, againſt the fears and threats of a very bold and huffie Adverſary, as you may read 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 32. Verſe 7. <hi>Be ſtrong and Couragious, be not afraid, nor diſmayed for the King of Aſſyria, nor for all the multitude that is with him: for there is moe with us then with him.</hi> Verſe 8. <hi>With him is an arm of fleſh, but with us is the Lord our God to help us, and to fight our battels.</hi> And while he made uſe of this excellent Remedy, for their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and Encouragement, under ſuch ſad Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, how ſuccesful was it for the relief of the ſpirits of that people: Therefore it is ſaid in the Latter part of the 8. Verſe. <hi>The People reſted themſelves upon the words of Hezekiah King of Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But did this great King, and his people reſt ſo upon the LORD, as to neglect the uſe of Ordinary means? No, for we ſee Verſe 5. <hi>That he ſtrengthned himſelf,</hi> by the uſe of all outward means, <hi>and built up all the wall that was broken, and he raiſed it up to the Towers, and another wall
<pb facs="tcp:153710:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>without, and repaired Millo in the City of David, and made Darts and Shields in abundance.</hi> And verſe 6. <hi>He ſet Captains of warr over the People, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them together to him in the ſtreet of the gate of the City:</hi> And yet he counted all theſe outward lawful means, but as a Quick ſand in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for you ſee in the 7. and 8. verſes, which we have read, he dropt his main Anchor upon the ROCK of Ages; And the Iſſue declared that he was no looſer thereby.</p>
            <p>I come in the next place to the uſe of the Doctrine. And firſt, <hi>It reproves one and all of us, in the different, Stations, Offices, and Circumſtances that we are into, for our negligence and unconcerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in carrying on this work of God, when ſuch a rich occaſion, and eminent call has been put in our hands.</hi> But if we will mourn for our bygone negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and amend our wayes for the future, and fall vigorouſly to this Reformation Work which my Text calls us to; then we may expect that <hi>God</hi> will pardon bypaſt neglects, when he ſees our future faithfulneſs and diligence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe is,</hi> To Exhort one and all of you. Eſpecially the Members of this Honourable and High Court of Parliament, carefully to ſet about this <hi>begun work of Reformation,</hi> and to take notice of <hi>Gods call</hi> to you this day, for this end and purpoſe: For, if I know any thing of the
<pb facs="tcp:153710:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>mind of GOD, this is the Meſſage he has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to deliver you, and what obedience ye give to it, the <hi>Divine Eye</hi> will certainly obſerve: And if ye will anſwer <hi>Gods call aright,</hi> there is a ſixfold Reformation, that all of us in our Stations muſt endeavour.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is, Perſonal Reformation, which <hi>God calls</hi> for at the Hands of every perſon in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, <hi>Ezeck:</hi> 18. Verſe 30. <hi>Pepent and turn your ſelves from all your Tranſgreſſions, ſo iniquity ſhall not be your ruine.</hi> And verſe 31. <hi>Caſt away from you, all your tranſgreſſions, whereby ye have tranſgreſſed, and make you a new Heart, and a new Spirit; for why will ye die, O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> And this perſonal Reformation is not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the <hi>Old,</hi> but alſo in the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7: 1: <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting Holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> Heb: 12.1. <hi>Let us lay aſide every weight, Yea, and our predominant ſins that ſo eaſily beſet us:</hi> All which Scriptures tells us, both the neceſſity of this Reformation, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of it, which ſhould awaken us unto great diligence and care there about.</p>
            <p>And as this perſonal Reformation is Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of GOD, ſo it is Commanded to others by thoſe that have tryed it, and found the good of it themſelves: as <hi>David</hi> did to his Son <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153710:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>and his Princes, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.19. <hi>Now ſet your heart, and your Soul to ſeek the LORD your GOD:</hi> And it is recorded to the Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Jehoſophat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro:</hi> 20.3 <hi>That he ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſeek the LORD</hi> Kings, Nobles, Gentrie, Miniſters and others, will be bad Reformers of ſuch as are under their Charge, who ſeek not the LORD themſelves: O that our Cloſets, our Conſciences, and our Converſations might be witneſſes to our Perſonal Reformation; It is clear enough from Scripture, that the LORD may make uſe of great Perſons for the Church, and Children, who yet may be Strangers unto perſonal Reformation them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as <hi>Jehu</hi> and <hi>Joaſh</hi> were but one of the beſt motives to make perſons in publick truſt, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the Reformation of others, is to be truely Reformed themſelves.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Second</hi> Reformation which we ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in our ſtation, and that is Family Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation what an Excellent patern, does <hi>David</hi> lay before us for this, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 101. Particularly the 7 <hi>Verſe, He that worketh in deceit, ſhall not dwell in my Houſe.</hi> And how is <hi>Abraham</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the LORD for this thing? <hi>Gen.</hi> 18 19 <hi>Verſe. For I know him that he will Command his houſehold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the LORD.</hi> O what a heavie Reckoning
<pb facs="tcp:153710:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>will many Maſters of Families and Parents meet with, for their neglect of this at the great day, beſides the Judgements that it draws down upon them, and their Families in this World: one Inſtance whereof ye have, not to name others. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.17 <hi>Verſe: And it ſhall be, that whoſe will not come up of all the Families of the Earth unto</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to worſhip the King, the LORD of Hoſts, even upon them ſhall be no rain.</hi> Which tells us, that perſons and families who make no Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to attend upon the publick Inſtituted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of GOD, it is to be feared that they are ſtrangers to a perſonal and family Reformation at home; whereas perſons that make Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of family Reformation will not dare to ſlight and neglect the publick Inſtituted worſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ip of GOD.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Third Reformation,</hi> That we ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in our ſtations, and that is <hi>Sanctuarie Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Hezekiah</hi> is an excellent pattern in this, who himſelf ſet about it ſo timeouſſie, 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 29.3. verſe, <hi>In the firſt year of his reign, in the firſt moneth did he open the doors of the houſe of the</hi> Lord, <hi>and commanded the rubbiſh to be taken out, and ſet up Prieſts and Officers therein, and gave them a ſtrict charge to mind their work;</hi> Lamenting the defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and corruptions that had crept into it: To this I may add the neceſſity and profitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:153710:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Univerſities and School Reformation, a thing greatly neceſſarie in order to Sanctuary and publick Reformation; For where Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Learning are tainted, they prove the Bane of the Church, and State alſo.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Fourth Reformation,</hi> That we ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in our Stations, is <hi>Judieatorie Reformation,</hi> That all the Judicatories in the Land, from the higheſt to the loweſt, may be reformed: for upon ſearch it will be found that many of them are not filled with ſuch perſons, as have ſound principles diſpoſing them to Advance the preſent work of Reformation, neither true loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie to their Majeſties, nor affection to the Eſtabliſhed Government, Great care therefore ſhould be taken by the <hi>ſupream Judicatorie</hi> of this Nation, that truth which is fallen in our ſtreets, &amp; Judgement, may be raiſed to their feet again, And that the iniquitie, oppreſſion, and Injuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, for which the Land mourns, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and we may have no more occaſion for that Complaint, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 59.14, 15. verſes, <hi>And judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is turned away backward, and Juſtice ſtandeth a farr of, for Truth is fallen in the ſtreets, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity cannot enter:</hi> You in whom is lodged the Supream Power, would take care, that the poor, who hang to long on, and cannot get their Cauſe diſcuſſed, may get Juſtice Execut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:153710:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeedily, and that without partiality.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly, You ſhould alſo take ſpecial Care, of Militarie, or Armie Reformation, that ſuch Officers only get and keep their Commiſſions, as are true to the Eſtabliſhed Government: You have had ſufficient warnings of theſe things already, to make you warry in time coming, but I muſt freely tell you that friendſhip Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and Covetouſneſs doth often ſpoile theſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> You are called in your Stations, to mind a National Reformation, that the <hi>LORD</hi> may be worſhipped according to the preſent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed Government (which is moſt ſuitable to the Word of <hi>GOD,</hi> and to which we ſtand greatly obliedged) from the one End unto the other, according to the Example of good <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſophat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 16: 4: <hi>And Jehoſophat dwelt at Jeruſalem, and be went out again through the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, from Beerſheba to Mount Ephraim, and brought them back unto the LORD GOD of their Fathers:</hi> Your Care and Zeal in this Matter would make you bear that excellent name in future Ages; <hi>The repairers of the Breach</hi> of the Church of <hi>Seotland,</hi> and <hi>the reſtorers of the Paths to dwell in, Iſa.</hi> 58: 12: This would be a mean to prevail with the <hi>LORD</hi> to come and dwell among us,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>and fill his Houſe with his Glory. Magiſtrates ſhould command it, Miniſters ſhould preach it, the People ſhould pray for it, and Souldiers overſee it, where it is needful: And if all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concerned would act Cordially and unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly with Reſolution and Couradge in their ſeveral Stations, as they are called and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed: I doubt not but our Land might yet be called <hi>JEHOVA Shamma,</hi> the LORD is there.</p>
            <p>But that I may ſhut up this Diſcourſe, I ſhall only add a few Motives; and but name them to preſs you to this Duty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt Motive</hi> is this, That if you whom GOD hath put in <hi>Publick Truſt,</hi> and Authority, take care to build GODS Houſe, ye ſhall be no looſer by it, for this is the way to engage GOD to build, and perpetuate your houſes: If ye will eſtabliſh His Throne, that he may reign in the Hearts of the Inhabitants of the Land, in &amp; by his own Ordinances; This will be a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Mean for eſtabliſhing the Kings Throne, <hi>Proverbs,</hi> 29: 14: <hi>Pſal:</hi> 89: 2: 3: 4: verſes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Motive</hi> is this, That the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to come, will bleſs you, who were Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in your places, to recover the Ruined Work of GOD in the Land, and to get the pure Goſpel Light ſet up every where: To let
<pb facs="tcp:153710:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Wilderneſs-Travellers ſee the way to the Kingdom: Will not the poſterity that came After us, &amp; get the good of this Reformation, ſay, bleſſed be ſuch a Noble family, and ſuch a Gentlemans family and poſterity, who laid out themſelves for the true worſhip of GOD, who when it was ready to be ſwallowed up and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, who recovered it out of the hand of the Enemie, and delivered it cleanly and ſafely down to us their poſterity, or elſe we had periſhed in ſuperſtition and darkneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This ſhould preſs you to a through and univerſal Refotmation in the Land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will be a notable Bulwark, to defend us from the invaſions of adverſaries, &amp; I lay it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you that are States men, and are for State policie, as one of Heavens politicks, for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Nation, under the proſpect of moſt imminent dangers, you have a tryed inſtance of this, 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 17.7. Alſo in the third year of <hi>Jehoſophats</hi> Reign, he ſent to his Princes, even to <hi>Banhael,</hi> and to <hi>Obadiah,</hi> and to <hi>Zechariab,</hi> &amp; to <hi>Nathaneel,</hi> and to <hi>Micajah,</hi> to teach in the citys of <hi>Judah,</hi> and with them he ſent <hi>Levites,</hi> verſe 8 and 9. <hi>They taught in Judah; and had the Book of the Law of the LORD with them, and went through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Cities of Judah, and taught the people:</hi> and the 10 verſe tells us, what a great ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:153710:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>it brought along with it, to the Land, <hi>For the Fear of the LORD, fell upon all the Kingdoms of the Lands that were round about Judah: ſo that they made no war againſt Jehoſophat,</hi> this you ſee is the ſweet advantage, that ariſes from true &amp; through Reformation, and ſhould not this move you to make uſe of it, and then you will have GOD's ſecurity, and GOD's ſecurity is the beſt ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Shew your ſelves therefore <hi>Men of Courage,</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> for GOD, and his cauſe, and intereſts, and ye need not queſtion, but he will be for you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> And I ſhall add no more, your being active and faithful for GOD &amp; his work, will upon a reflection, even under troubles and tryals in this World, be verie ſupporting, and refreſhing, But <hi>O</hi> What a cordial will it be in a dying houre, when all the Compoſitions of Apothecaties have loſt their Reliſh, &amp; when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Riches, nor Honours, nor pleaſures of this World, will have any ſignificancie: with good <hi>Hezekiah, Iſaiah,</hi> 38: 2, 3. verſes. <hi>Turn your faces to the wall, &amp; pray, Remember now, O</hi> LORD, <hi>I beſeech Thee, how I have walked before Thee in Truth, and with a perfect Heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> I ſay this will be the Great ſupport, and Conſolations of your hearts, who are perſons of publick truſt, when ye come to
<pb facs="tcp:153710:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>the laſt ſtep, between time &amp; eternitie: Let me therefore with all humility and earneſtneſs, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, O <hi>Zerubabel,</hi> his Majeſties high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, &amp; you who are the Officers of State, and you the reſt of the Members of this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parliament, in the words of my Text, Yet <hi>Now, O Zerubabel, be ſtrong, ſaith the LORD, and be ſtrong O Joſhua, Son of Joſedech the high Prieſt; and be ſtrong all ye people of the land, ſaith the LORD; and work, for I am with you, ſaith the LORD of Hoſts;</hi> Even ſo be it. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:35"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:35"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Col: <hi>4.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And ſay to <hi>Archippus,</hi> take heed to the Miniſtrie which thou haſt received in the LORD; that thou fulfill it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Occaſion of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> his writing this Epiſtle from <hi>Rome,</hi> while he was Priſoner there, unto this Church of <hi>Colloſſe</hi> ſeems to be from the Information he bad by <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras</hi> the Miniſter of the place, holding furth the danger, that, that Church was into, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing corrupted both in her principles and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and that as well from Jews upon the one hand, as Gentiles upon the other.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles ſcope in this Epiſtle, is to confirm them, in the Doctrine Preached by <hi>Epaphras,</hi> their honeſt Miniſter, and to preſs them to the further knowledge &amp; practice of Godlineſs; and that both as to the General and ſpecial duties of
<pb facs="tcp:153710:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſtianity, in the concluſion of this Epiſtle, which is from the 9 Verſe to the End. We have ſeveral ſalutations, wherein ſome are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted and Commended as Verſes 10.11. Some ſaluted and exhorted, that they may ſtand per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and compleat in all the will of GOD, as <hi>Verſe</hi> 12: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some are ſaluted and directed, as <hi>Verſe</hi> 16, and ſome are ſaluted and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as in this Text: <hi>And ſay to</hi> Archippus, <hi>Take heed to the Miniſtrie which thou haſt received in the LORD, that thou fulfill it.</hi> As if the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would ſay to the People, Commend me alſo to <hi>Archippus</hi> your Miniſter, and tell him from me, to take heed that he do not his work careleſlie, and by halfs; But as he has received his Commiſſion from the LORD, ſo let him fulfil it, and that by the conſtant and diligent performing of all the duties belonging to ſo great and weighty a Charge.</p>
            <p>Whither this <hi>Archippus</hi> was Collegue to <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras,</hi> or whither he was Paſtor of the <hi>Laodecean</hi> Church, (as ſome Interpreters aſſert, and the connexion with the proceeding verſe, ſeems to favour it) I ſhall not determine, and it is a matter of no great importance; for wherever he was Miniſter, it is like he was fallen Remiſs in his Office, A Fault, that I fear too too many of us may be charged with, which remiſſnes
<pb facs="tcp:153710:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>flows ſometimes I conceive from prevalent cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption within, and too much love of the world without, As alſo from theſe diſcouragements that Miniſters often meet with from their people, either upon the account of their unprofitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, under the means and pains beſtowed upon them, or upon the account of that oppoſition which their people make to the work of GOD among their hands.</p>
            <p>Thir words at firſt view, fall into two parts, <hi>viz.</hi> an injunction and a meſſage, The injunction is to the people, in theſe words, and ſay to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cbippus,</hi> the meſſage they are to tell him from the Apoſtle, <hi>is to take heed to his Miniſtrie, how he has received it, and how he may fulfil it aright.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this verſe being an Exhortation, contains more particularly in it theſe four things, Firſt, The perſon exhorted, the <hi>Lazie Miniſter.</hi> 2. The thing he is exhorted <hi>to take heed to thy Miniſtry,</hi> &amp;c. 3. We have the Arguments preſſing this heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs: 1. Its a truſt, and perſons muſt take heed to their truſt, becauſe it is not ſo much their own matters, as others they are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned about. 2. It is a great truſt that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have committed to them, when they have the Precious, and Immortal Souls of Men, to take care about.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing in the words, is the <hi>modus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153710:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>or the manner how he is to notice and manage this Miniſtry, he is to heed it and manage it ſo, as to fulfil it. And theſe that would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge this Office aright, muſt carefully mind not only the Extenſiveneſs, but alſo the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs of this Work, for the meer tale of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will not be ſufficient to fulfil this Miniſtry, except they have their proportionable weight and meaſure, even ſuch as will make them paſs, when tryed and weighted in the ballance of the Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>Thir words affoords us three Doctrines; the firſt Doctrine is this, That People perceiving their Miniſter fail in the Office of his Miniſtry, may and ought to admoniſh him, but in Love, and with all due reſpect to his Perſon and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, 1 <hi>Timothy</hi> 5.1. <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort him as a Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There is no power of Jurisdiction in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from this Text, to inflict Church Cenſures on their Miniſter: For all that is ſaid here, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth no more, then ſuch an admonition as any private Chriſtian may give him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Doctrine is, That great Heedful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is required of Miniſters in order to the right diſcharge of their Office.</p>
            <p>The third Doctrine is, That among other Conſiderations preſſing us to fulfil this Miniſtry,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>this ſhould be none of the leaſt, that we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it of the LORD.</p>
            <p>Of the firſt Doctrine I ſhall ſay no more, and this third Obſervation will be touched in the Proſecution of the ſecond, which is that I ſhall inſiſt upon, as being moſt proper to this Occaſion.</p>
            <p>And that I may doe it as briefly as poſſible, I ſhall in the firſt place ſhew you ſome of theſe Qualifications implyed in this Heedfulneſs (that the Text calls for) which are neceſſary to the right fulfilling of a Mans Miniſtrie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall give you the Reaſons of the Doctrine, and thirdly the uſe of All.</p>
            <p>The firſt Qualification then implyed here, as neceſſary to make a Miniſter take heed to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage his Office a right is, Wiſdom and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and that not only in the Speculative, but in the practical part of Religion. I think both theſe are needful to make a Miniſter <hi>apt to teach,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. or elſe his Miniſtry will be rather Art-work, then Heart-work. Unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied witts have been in all Ages greatly prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to the Church, and we have not wanted ſad Inſtances thereof in our day.</p>
            <p>I ſay then, that the Miniſters of Chriſt, muſt be men of Knowledge, for they are Watchmen, and Watchmen muſt have Eyes in their Head,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore they are <hi>called Seers,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.9: Come let us go to the Seer, they are to point out to the People their Way, their Danger, and their Duty, as we may alſo ſee from <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 21. and 6. <hi>Verſe</hi> to the 13. <hi>Verſe, And if they be blind, what hurt may ſuddenly befall the Church,</hi> Iſaiah 9. <hi>Verſe</hi> 16. <hi>For the leaders of this People cauſe them to Erre, and they that are led of them are deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ignorance cauſes Error, and Error Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, therefore ſaid the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Epheſus, Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Take heed therfore unto your ſelves, and to all the flock, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers, to feed them, viz:</hi> With Knowledge and Underſtanding, that they may be ſoundly principled, &amp; right in the Faith, and he gives the reaſon of it, <hi>Verſes</hi> 29. and 30. <hi>For grievous wolves will enter in amongſt you, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perverſe things to corrupt your People, and to draw Diſciples after them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miniſters ſhould be like the beaſts about Chriſts Throne, <hi>Rev:</hi> 4.6. <hi>Full of Eyes within and without, before and behind:</hi> Within looking to the Frame and Conſtitution of their own Hearts, without to the Duties they ought to perform, and the Snares and Dangers they muſt beware of, in following of their Duty: They muſt have Eyes looking before them unto God for Counſel and Direction, and they muſt have
<pb facs="tcp:153710:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>eyes looking behind them unto the flocks which they lead. Every Miniſter is as it were the Treaſurer of the place where he lives, <hi>Malachy</hi> 2.7. <hi>For the Prieſts lips ſhould keep Knowledge, and the people ſhould ſeek the law at his mouth,</hi> and if the Miniſters want this Treaſurie of Spiritual know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Wiſdom, they will not be able to diſtinguiſh aright between Truth and Errour, Sin and Duty: They cannot inſtruct the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, reſolve doubts, quiet the troubled Conſcience feed the Hungry, &amp; comfort the <hi>diſcouraged Soul.</hi> Let <hi>Antichriſt</hi> have blind and ignorant Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but Our LORD JESUS CHRIST ſhould have ſuch Miniſters as are throughly furniſhed for every Good Work, 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3: 17: <hi>That the Man of GOD may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all Good Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Qualification implyed in this <hi>Take heed,</hi> (for a Miniſters right diſcharging of his Office) is painfulneſs and diligence, for knowledge muſt iſſue unto action: Miniſters are Angels, and Angels are not only full of Eyes (as I ſaid before) but alſo full of Hands and Wings. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 1: 8: <hi>And they had the Hands of a Man under their Wings on their four ſides,</hi> &amp;c: Therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Rev:</hi> 4: 8: <hi>That they reſt not day nor night,</hi> they know much, therefore they Act much.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The Heathen could tell us that unpractical knowledge ſignifies nothing, <hi>Scire tuum nihil eſt, niſi te ſcire hoc ſciat alter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> painted a Tongue with a hand under it to ſhew that knowledge, when practiced was good. And we ſee that the bleſſing is not promiſed to the bare knowledge, but to the practice of Commanded duties, <hi>John.</hi> 13.17. <hi>If ye know theſe things, happie are ye if you do them, and</hi> Rev: 22. Verſe 14. <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his Commandments, that they may have Right to the Tree of Life, and enter in through the Gates unto the City.</hi> We are Spiritual harveſt men, and the Crop is very precious, which we are to gather in, If it be loſt by our ſloath, we will pay dear for it.</p>
            <p>The third qualification implyed here (in this, <hi>Take heed to your Miniſtrie</hi>) is faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: O how much need had we to take heed that we do our Miniſterial work faithfullie, now faithfulneſs is a proportioning our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Command: to be impartial in all the Adminiſtrations of the houſe of GOD: See what a charge the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> gives <hi>Timothie,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. <hi>I Charge thee before GOD, and the LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, and the elect Angels that thou obſerve theſe things without preferring one before another, doing nothing by partialitie.</hi> Where we ſee
<pb facs="tcp:153710:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>that he that is partial cannot be faithful, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful Miniſter is perfidious both to GOD and man. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.4. <hi>It is ſaid there, their Prophets are light and Treacherous perſons:</hi> Treacherous Perſons in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> as a Learned Interpreter obſerves, is <hi>Viri Praevaricationum qui debitam Deo &amp; populo fidem pariter violaverint.</hi> And it is the higheſt Treacherie that can be, to be falſe to GOD and Robb Him of the Souls of men; That is worthy of our Conſideration recorded. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 3.20. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt not given him warning; He ſhall die in his ſin, but his Blood ſhall I require at thine hand.</hi> Now if a Miniſter may Periſh for not warning of Sinners, much more for Encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aging them to Sin, by corrupt Doctrine, and a Lewd life, for If death be in an Gmiſſion, much more muſt it be in poſitive Evils. Let me add one word more on this head, that a faithful mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, muſt be a fearleſs Miniſter, he muſt not be affraid of the faces of men, when he is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Truths of GOD. The LORD four times in one <hi>Verſe. Ezek.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Forbids the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to fear. And thou Son of man be not affraid of them, neither be affraid of their words, though Briers and Thorns be with thee, and thou doeſt dwell among Scorphions: Be not affraied of their words, nor diſmayed at their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooks, though they be a Rebellious Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Fourth qualification neceſſarie for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aging
<pb facs="tcp:153710:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>this office implyed in this exhortation <hi>(take heed to thy Miniſtry)</hi> is prudence which is neceſſarie to direct us in the dexterous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of all the parts of our work, and more eſpecially as to the Methods whereby, and the Seaſons wherein they may be done to the beſt advantage, and there is no part of our Miniſterial work, which requires more pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the right managing of it, then that of Reproof, to do that ſo as it may be accepted as a kindneſs by the perſon reproved, and as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Oyle that will not break the head, as the Pſalmiſt expreſſes it. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 141. <hi>Verſe,</hi> 5. <hi>Let the Righteous Smite me, it ſhall be a kindneſs; and let them reprove me, it ſhall be an excellent Oyl; which ſhall not break my head:</hi> For as faithfulneſs and wiſdom ponders the neceſſity of the duty; So prudence does conſider the fitteſt time, and manner of application with reſpect to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, with what prudence and dexteritie did <hi>Nathan</hi> prepare <hi>David</hi> in that Parable. 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 12. from the firſt <hi>Verſe</hi> to the 6th. before he came to touch him in the quick with; <hi>Thou art the man, Verſe</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, if we would take heed to fulfil this Miniſtrie, we muſt be ſincere and ſerious <hi>Ecleſ:</hi> 9.10. And it is not Liklie that we will preſs Goſpel Truths and holineſs, ſeriouſly home
<pb facs="tcp:153710:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon others, until we know the ſweet and good of them our ſelves, and the Apoſtle tells us. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.12. <hi>Verſe.</hi> That ſincerity in our work and walk will be no ſmal ground of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, when our conſciences within, and beholders without can teſtifie, that we endeav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oured ſincerely and carefully to Manage this truſt committed to us, and Miniſters had need to take heed to this, becauſe their work lying about ſpiritual things they are more apt to be deceived by hypocriſies creeping in both to their hearts and duties, and many a time the frequencie of them, is like to take away the fervencie of them: Miniſters therefore would often mind that word, to keep them diligent at their work, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 9.27. <hi>Leaſt when I preach the Goſpel to others, I my ſelf be a caſt away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6ly. This <hi>take heed,</hi> includes conſtancie and perſervance, we muſt not think to do this work by fits and ſtarts; Nor be like theſe <hi>fooliſh Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Galatians</hi> 3 <hi>chap.</hi> and 3 <hi>ver. To begin in the ſpirit, and end in the fleſh,</hi> we muſt not put our hand to the plough and look back, Ye know what CHRIST ſays of ſuch, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.62. <hi>They are not fit for the Kingdom of GOD,</hi> they are not fit for managing of his Kingdom aright in this world, and if they do not that, they may be affraid to be ſhut out of his Kingdom in the next.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> I come next to the Reaſons of the doctrine, why Miniſters muſt be very heedfull, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full about their Miniſterial work, and that 1ſt. Becauſe it is a great truſt far above any other truſt in this world, when immortal Souls are committed to us, about which the thoughts of the moſt high have been concerned from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and for the Redemption of which GOD manifeſted in the fleſh, ſhed his precious blood: &amp; for eſpouſing of whom he has put us unto the Miniſtrie. I think we ſhould never go this er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, but with <hi>Abrahams ſervant. Gen.</hi> 24 12. <hi>We ſhould pray, O LORD GOD and Father of My Maſter JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> (Who has promiſed him a great backing and a numerous ſeed, upon which he may ſee the ſatisfaction of the travel of his Soul) ſend me good ſpeed this day, and put forth thy power in the preached Goſpel, that Thy people may be a willing people, O but it be a high and a great calling to trade about the ſaving of Souls, one of which is a more precious Jewel than the whole world can purchaſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem, And CHRIST tells us this out of his own Mouth, <hi>Matth:</hi> 16.26. <hi>Surely of all other perſons Miniſters ſhould be moſt diligent, who have both their own Souls to ſave, and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon why we muſt take heed to our Miniſterial work is, becauſe it is a difficult
<pb facs="tcp:153710:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>work, partly from the various and numerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that oppoſe it, Satan that roaring lion, and reſtleſs enemie of the Church ſtanding at our right hand. <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.1. Alſo what principaliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and powers and ſpiritual wickedneſſeſs in high places, what rulers of the darkneſs of this world have we to wreſtle againſt. <hi>Eph:</hi> 6.12, yea what oppoſition from men among whom we live, ſome with open violence breaking down as far as they can the carved work: others under a vizour and pretence to build with us, like the falſe apoſtles; intending nothing leſs then to bring us back to abandoned Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Houſe of GOD.</p>
            <p>Partly from our own Ignorance (the work is made difficult) which diſables us to manage this truſt to the beſt advantage, how hard is it for Miniſters to ſpeake aright to the various Caſes and Conditions of their People, and to find fitt words to hold forth the Evil of Sin by, the Lovelineſs of Chriſt, The beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the danger of living careleſly and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernedly under the means of Grace, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated offers of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The third Reaſon why Miniſters had need to take heed to their Miniſtry is this, that there has been Miniſters in the Church, (and we have had ſad Inſtances of it in our days) profeſſing &amp; pretending highly for CHRIST, and the pureſt
<pb facs="tcp:153710:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>work of Reformation, that afterwards when the Occaſion and Tentation offered, have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the cauſe, diſcovered their rottenneſs, and ruined the Church, and Work of GOD, as far as they could. Some of them bewitched and enticed with the Riches of this World ſo to do, like <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Demas:</hi> Others with the Honours of this World, like <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> and O how many <hi>Archippus</hi>-like even in the beſt of times would be found <hi>Coldriffe</hi> and <hi>Remiſſe</hi> in this great Work.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. We muſt take heed to our Miniſtry, if we conſider what a great LORD and Maſter we have received it from. And whoſe Eye is alwayes upon us, to ſee how we manage this truſt as it was upon the Angels of the ſeven Churches, and his writting to them ſince he Aſcended, and diſcovering their failures and ſhort comings, with the puniſhments due thereunto, ſhould be a warning to Miniſters in all ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ages of the Church, to take heed to their Miniſtrie.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly We had need to take heed to our Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, when we conſider with what a ſevere certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, our great LORD and Maſter has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it unto us, <hi>Ezek:</hi> 17, 18. <hi>ver. Son of man I have made thee a Watchman to the houſe of Iſrael, therefore bear the word at my mouth, and give them
<pb facs="tcp:153710:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>a warning from me, when I ſay unto the wicked thou ſhalt ſurelie die, and thou giveſt him not warning from me, nor ſpeakeſt to warn the Wicked from his wicked way, to ſave his life, the ſame wicked man ſhall die in his iniquitie, but his blood will I require at thine hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6ly Miniſters had need to take heed to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadge their truſt aright, ſeeing a ſevere account will be required of them, for it is a ſtewardſhip that muſt be reckoned for, and none of us know how ſoon that meſſage may be ſent unto us, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.2. <hi>Give an account of thy Stewardſhip, and whether we have received moe or fewer talents, we would alwayes remember to be ſo laying them out, and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of them, as thoſe that muſt give an account. Heb.</hi> 13: 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly.</hi> Such Miniſters as have been heedfull and faithfull, ſhall be greatly rewarded, <hi>Dan:</hi> 12 3 <hi>And they that be Wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the firmament, and they that turn many to righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, as the ſtarrs for ever and ever. Matt:</hi> 24.25, 26, 27. <hi>who then is a faithfull and wiſe ſervant, whom his Lord hath made ruler over his houſhold to give them meat in due ſeaſon, Bleſsed is that ſervant whom his LORD when he cometh ſhall find him ſo doing; Verily I ſay unto you, that he ſhall make him Ruler over all his goods.</hi> Rev: 2.10. <hi>Be thou faithful unto the death, and I will give thee a Crown of life.</hi> We would keep conſtantly and cloſely to this
<pb facs="tcp:153710:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>work, and proſecute it with the greateſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that believe ſuch a reward as this, which will eternaly compenſe all the labour and toyle in this World: We would alſo frequently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what ſevere puniſhments ſhall be inflicted on the heedleſs and ſloathful ſervant, <hi>Matt:</hi> 24 <hi>Verſe</hi> 48. Unto the end; <hi>But, and if that evil ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſhall ſay my Lord delayeth his coming, and ſhall begin to ſmite his fellow ſervant, and to eat and drink with the drunken. The Lord of that ſervant ſhall come in a day, when he Looketh not for him, and an hour that he is not aware of, and ſhall cut him aſunder, and appoint him his portion with hypocrites, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> come now to the uſe of the Doctrine, <hi>is heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,</hi> in managing of the Miniſterial work ſo neceſſary in all the forementioned reſpects; Then let all of us that bear this office take heed to out Miniſtry, for this is the voice and call of my Text to every one of us, and eſpecially with reſpect to thoſe two things that ly in the latter part of the words.</p>
            <p>The firſt is to take heed how, and from whom we received this Miniſtrie, whether from the LORD JESUS CHRIST or not, who is the only LORD and head of the Church, and whoſe prerrogative it is to ſet up and ſend forth Officers unto his Church, <hi>Ezek:</hi> 2 3. <hi>And He ſaid unto him Son of man, I ſend thee unto the
<pb facs="tcp:153710:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>Children of Iſrael, I Who ſit upon the Saphirine throne,</hi> as you have it in the firſt Chapter of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Ezek:</hi> 26: <hi>Verſe, And who has all power in mine hand.</hi> Chriſt is inveſted with all power in Heaven and in Earth, <hi>Matth:</hi> 28: and 18: <hi>Verſe, and therefore ſends forth Officers unto all Nations.</hi> And for this End, we muſt ſee that we be come in at the right door, for there are ſome, as Chriſt tells us, who call themſelves Sheepherds, that come not in at this doar, <hi>Jo:</hi> 10: 1: <hi>Verſe, But climb up another way,</hi> if we be right Miniſters of Chriſt, we muſt come in at three doors. 1. The door of an Internal call of GOD upon the Soul. 2. The door of the External call of the People. 3. The door of a legal <hi>Miſſion</hi> and <hi>Ordination, by the laying on of the hands of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond thing that lyes in the latter end of the Text, about which we muſt take ſpecial heed is this, that when ever we find out ſelves entered by the right door unto this great and difficult Work, we muſt take heed to fulfil it: Every Miniſter muſt take heed to fill up a right both the doing part, and the ſuffering part of his Miniſtry, ſo as the work may not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer or be blamed on his Accompt: The Apoſtle took care of this, and ſets it as a Copy before thir <hi>Colloſſians,</hi> Chapter firſt,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>24: <hi>Verſe, Who now rejoyce in my ſufferings for you, and fill up that which is behind of the Afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions of Chriſt, in my fleſh, for his bodies ſake, which is the Church.</hi> The metaphor may be taken from a piece of curious drawn work, that the perſon, in filling up thereof, never puts in a ſtitch, but they look on both ſides to ſee it be rightly done, and they Papper it over to keep it cleanly that they may get the maſters appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, ſo ſhould both Miniſters and Chriſtians be very careful, both in their doing and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work, that they fill it up with all dexteritie, and keep it ſo as it may be preſented with all purity; For I do believe that GOD has cut out ſo much doing and ſuffering work for his Church in the world, and that this is divided and ſubdivided to ſeveral Societies, and Perſons, every one their part: So much for the Church in ſuch an Age and place of the World, and ſo much for ſuch an other Age and place of the World, and every Perſon ought to notice what is their particular allotment, that they may do it both proportionably, and commendablie, and not be like an Ignorant, careleſs, and neſty ſeamſter, to whom in a ſuit of curious Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings was committed: The doing of a head, or a hand, or a Leg, and when it comes to be ſet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, it is either not filled up, or diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable,
<pb facs="tcp:153710:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>or fullied, and ſo mars the beauty of the whole ſuite, and when the maſter comes in and ſees how unhandſome it is, and calls the perſons guilty; How will they be aſhamed? with what care then ſhould Miniſters and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that profeſs Religion, to obey GODS Commands, and follow the noble Example of CHRIST and His Apoſtles, ſo mind to fill up what proportion, of either doing or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work that is committed to them as they may be able to abide the tryal of that day, and not be aſhamed. This is that which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to call all the People of GOD to, both miniſters and others in this Text, with reſpect to the doing part, and in that of the firſt Chapter 24 <hi>Verſe,</hi> formerly cited as to the ſuff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering part, but alace this is too little heeded by many.</p>
            <p>Now that we may diſcharge our Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al work well; Let me Intreat our care as to theſe four things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us take care to be well ſeen in all parts of our work, the Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and Government of the Church; and the Duties Relating to theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us be well ſeen into the caſes of our People, that we may know how to inſtruct, Exhort, Reprove, and warn them both ſuitably
<pb facs="tcp:153710:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſeaſonably, as to their various caſes and Conditions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In the doing of theſe things, let us alwayes keep our eye upon the right Rule, which we are to work and walk by; every Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling has ſome Rule to work by, which requires ſome Studie to know, or elſe a Perſon will but Bungle in his work. Now no calling hath a ſure Rule, but the Chriſtian calling, therefore it is that others varie in their Methods: But the Chriſtian hath one ſtanding Rule (The word of GOD) which is able to make the man of GOD perfect: this we muſt preciſely keep by, and muſt not make the impoſitions of men, Education, Cuſtome, Example, or Antiquity, our Rule, or any part of it, which the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> pleads. <hi>Job:</hi> 4.20. For the juſtification of their worſhip in Mount <hi>Geriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zim,</hi> being two hundred Years ſtanding, But CHRIST Told her, <hi>Verſe.</hi> 22. <hi>Ye Worſhip ye know not what,</hi> you have the wills, Examples, and Traditions of men for the warrant of your worſhip, but that is neither Law nor Light, nor Rule to you, ſeeing ye want my word which is the true Standart, and your good Intentions will neither make that worſhip which you dote upon acceptable to GOD, or profitable to you: For all Corrupt and falſe worſhip
<pb facs="tcp:153710:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>carries no other Character in the Eſtimation of GOD, but ſuch as is recorded. <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Ephraim compaſſeth me about with lies, and the houſe of Iſrael with deceit;</hi> we would bewar of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that number, and endeavour to be of the tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> which ruleth with GOD, and is faithfull with the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> If we would fulfill our Miniſtrie aright, <hi>Let us wreſtle much with the LOKD for his promiſed Spirit</hi> to teach us all things that concern the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of ſo great an office, to put us and keep us in a right frame for our work, to inſtruct us by a ſtrong hand both what, and, how to ſpeak to our people: And that he would make it firſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorie to our own Souls, and then go along with us in the diſpenſing of the word &amp; ſeale it on the hearts of the hearers; for the Kings meſſage is beſt belived &amp; obeyed when it has the King's ſeal at it, then peoples faith will not ſtand in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Mans words, but in the power of GOD. 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.4.5. <hi>And my ſpeech and my preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was not with enticing words of mans wiſdom, but in demonſtration of the ſpirit, and of power, that your faith may not ſtand in the wiſdom of man, but in the power of God.</hi> And in the whole of our work, let us chiefly aim at the good of Souls, the enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of CHRIST's Kingdom, and the Glory of GOD, <hi>from Whom, and by Whom, and to Whom are all things, to Him be Glorie for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:47"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:47"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:48"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153710:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
